[Thrun] Here's my code:
这是我的代码
If you've got this correct,
如果你做对了
then I'm mightily impressed with what you've done because
我会为你感到非常骄傲
you've taken something that often takes many, many classes
因为你完成的这项任务 往往需要很多堂课
to explain to students, and within a single class,
才能解释清楚 而你却只上了一堂课
you understood the gist of it and you wrote a piece of code
就了解了其精髓所在 并写出了一段
that is really non-trivial, that you can reuse many times,
非常关键的代码 而且这段代码可以多次重用
and that's the core of the Google self-driving cars' ability to check other vehicles.
这是谷歌的无人驾驶车能够追踪其他车辆的核心所在
Here is the line by line implementation
这是逐行实现
of what I've shown you before for the measurement update
我之前说过的测量值更新和预测
and the prediction, and you'll find
你会发现
using my matrix class that it implements
它使用我的矩阵类准确地
step after step exactly what I've shown you.
逐步实现了我展示过的内容
A little non-triviality.
非常不简单
We have to make a measurement matrix of the nth measurement.
我们必须对第 n 次测量创建测量矩阵
If you solve the problem, you have probably something like this.
这个问题求解时 你可能会这样
The error calculation,
误差计算
the matrix S with a transpose,
计算矩阵 S 时用到了转置
the Kalman gain K with the inverse,
计算卡尔曼增益 K 时用到了求逆矩阵
back to my next prediction and my measurement update,
回到我下面的预测和测量值更新
and this is the prediction step.
然后 这是预测步骤
You can see it implements exactly what I showed you
你可以看到 它准确实现了我在这里
in these two equations over here.
的两个方程中所展现的内容
Now I know programming with this is involved,
我知道这里涉及到编程
and I'm really impressed if you were able to do this.
如果你能完成 我会非常吃惊
If you've done this, you've achieved something really, really major.
如果你已经完成好 说明你已取得了令人赞叹的成就
You now understand Kalman filters,
你现在已经理解了卡尔曼滤波器
and you've implemented a multidimensional Kalman filter
并且使用我给你写的非常机械的矩阵类
all on your own using a fairly mechanical
实现了一个多维
matrix class that I wrote for you.
卡尔曼滤波器
You ran it, and it's gotten really good results
你运行了这个滤波器 结果非常好
in which a sequence of position estimates: 1, 2, 3,
一系列的位置预测 1、2、3
led you to make a prediction
让你做出了预测
and understand the velocity of the moving object.
并了解了移动对象的速度
These are the equations you just implemented.
这些是你刚刚实现的方程式
Congratulations.
祝贺你！
You really understood something fundamental here
你已经真正理解了这些基础知识
that I believe is really essential to artificial intelligence
而这些是人工智能和
and to building self-driving cars.
打造无人驾驶车的必备知识
You implemented effectively our method for finding other cars.
你有效地实现了寻找其他车辆的方法
Let me put this in context.
下面 我为这个方法提供一个场景
Here's a Google self-driving car.
这是一台谷歌的无人驾驶车
Here's another car.
这是另一辆车
Our Google self-driving car uses radar on the front bumper
我们的谷歌无人驾驶车使用前保险杠上的雷达
that measures the distance to vehicles
来测量与其他车辆的距离
and also gives a noisy estimate of the velocity.
同时给出了估计速度时的误差
And it also uses its lasers,
它还同时使用激光雷达
and again, it measures the distance to other cars but no velocities.
测量与其他车辆的距离 但没测量速度
If you take the same situation from above,
在上面同样的场景中
here is the Google car.
这里是谷歌的车
It is localized on a map.
它位于地图上的某一点
Here is another vehicle, and another one.
这是另一辆车 还有另一辆
Using radars and lasers, the Google car estimates the distance
谷歌的车使用雷达和激光估算
and the velocity of all these vehicles,
所有这些车辆的距离和速度
and it does so using a Kalman filter.
这个过程中借助了卡尔曼滤波器
Where it feeds in range data from the laser,
我们获得了来自激光雷达的距离数据
and it uses state spaces like this one of the relative distance in x and y
并且使用了状态空间 如这个 x 和 y的相对距离
and the relative velocity in x and y to get state transition matrices
以及 x 和 y 的相对速度 得到了我刚才展示的
of the type I've just shown you to find out
类型的状态转移矩阵
where these other cars are, and this is exactly what you've just learned
最终找到了其他车辆的位置 这就是你刚刚
and programmed yourself.
学习和编程的内容
I didn't tell you how to extract the location of other cars from radar and laser.
我没有告诉你如何从雷达和激光数据中提取位置
There's something called a correspondence problem.
我们把这个问题叫做对应点问题（correspondence problem）
Sometimes you don't know which one each car is,
有时候 你不知道哪辆车是哪辆车
and I won't talk in much depth about it.
我们这里不深入探讨
But you understand the gist of the solution now,
但你已经知道了这个解决方案的核心
and you've been able to program it.
而且能够编程实现了
If you were in a situation like this,
如果你碰到这种场景
you can use range data like laser data and radar data
你可以使用距离数据 如激光和雷达数据
and come up with a rational algorithm that takes
并创建一个合理的算法 利用
momentary measurements of other cars
其他车辆的瞬时测量值
and not just estimates where they are but also how fast they're moving.
而不是车辆位置的估算值 再加上车辆速度
That's really a tremendous feat.
这是了不起的成就
Congratulations on getting this far.
祝贺你取得巨大进步
If you got this far in my class,
既然你已经学到了这里
I promise you you've just digested the most difficult thing
我向你保证 你刚刚掌握了
I have to teach you in this entire class.
这堂课上最困难的一部分
Congratulations.
祝贺你！